{"tossups": [{"question": "Inmates at the Prison of the Annamites in this department revolted against poor conditions in Inini. In the 1880s, this region fought a border-war with Brazil over the independent state of Counani. A man cried \"Long live France! Long live the Army!\" after being sentenced to life imprisonment in a penal colony in this region, from which Henri Charri\u00e8re [[shah-ree-YAY]] escaped, as recounted in his novel <em>Papillon</em> [[pah-pee-YOHN]]. The European Space Agency constructed its primary space center in , for ten points, what French overseas region, where Alfred Dreyfus was imprisoned on Devil\u2019s Island.", "answer": "<b><u>French Guiana</u></b> (accept La <b><u>Guyane Fran\u00e7aise</u></b>; prompt on \"Devil's Island\" before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man is the subject of a work by Joseph Califano titled <em>The Triumph and Tragedy</em> <em>of</em> [this man], and over 400 collections of manuscripts were relied upon by Robert Dalleck in another biography of this man. A four-volume series, including such entries as <em>The Passage</em> <em>of Power</em> and <em>Master of the Senate</em>, was written about this one-time Speaker of the House. For ten points, Robert Caro wrote that four-volume biography of what man who took the presidential oath on an airplane?", "answer": "<b><u>L</u></b>yndon B(aines) <b><u>Johnson</u></b> (accept <b><u>LBJ</u></b>; prompt on \u201cJohnson\u201d)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This monarch appointed Edward Courtenay, 1st Earl of Devon, royal envoy to Holy Roman Emperor Charles V but rejected his ambition for the throne. Robert Aske led a popular revolt, known as the Pilgrimage of Grace, aiming to restore this royal to the English line of succession. Phillip II of Spain used his marriage to this daughter of Catherine of Aragon as a pretext to invade the British Isles in the 1580s. The English Reformation was nearly undone by, for ten points, what \"Bloody\" queen of the Tudor Dynasty, the sister of Elizabeth I?", "answer": "<b><u>Mary</u></b> I (or <b><u>Mary</u></b> Tudor; accept Bloody <b><u>Mary</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This politician justified the use of force during colonization efforts in his \"Report on Algeria,\" written during Algerian occupation by the army of King Louis Philippe. This man wrote about the disconnection between the hereditary nobility and rural peasant leading to the disintegration of the Ancien R\u00e9gime [[ahn-SHYAHN reh-ZHEEM]] in <em>The Old Regime and</em> <em>the Revolution</em>. This man also collected data for a book while ostensibly on a tour of U.S.  prisons. For ten points, name this French aristocrat and author of <em>Democracy in America</em>.", "answer": "Alexis de <b><u>Tocqueville</u></b> (or Alexis Charles Henri Cl\u00e9rel, comte de <b><u>Tocqueville</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "In 1980, this state's Lake Peigneur was contaminated when an oil rig hit a salt mine, making the water brackish. Edwin Edwards served four terms as governor of this state and won one election with the slogan \"Vote for the lizard, not the wizard\" while campaigning against KKK Grand Wizard David Duke. The \"Share Our Wealth\" program was advocated by a governor of this state whom Robert Penn Warren called a \"Dictator.\" Huey Long once governed, for ten points, what Bayou State?", "answer": "<b><u>Louisiana</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In this empire's chronology, the phrase \"the king who lived in tents\" is used to refer to its first domestic rulers, beginning with Tudiya. The practice of deporting hostile ethnic groups was introduced by Shalmaneser I, a king of this empire, following his conquest of the Mitanni. The fields of Susa were sown with salt following a humiliation inflicted by the Elamites on this empire's people, resulting in that violent act by Ashurbanipal. The city of Assur served as the capital of, for ten points, what Mesopotamian empire of Sargon II and Sennacherib [[seh-NAH-keh-rib]]?", "answer": "<b><u>Assyria</u></b>n Empire (or <b><u>Assyria</u></b>ns; accept Neo-<b><u>Assyria</u></b>n Empire)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "This structure was completed in 1957 under the direction of William H. Pickering, and flooding nearly destroyed the particle accelerator chamber in which the data tapes for this structure were archived. This structure was equipped with a cosmic ray detector co-designed by graduate students in a basement of a physics building. The radiation belts that this structure discovered were named after physicist James Van Allen. For ten points, what was this first satellite launched by NASA?", "answer": "<b><u>Explorer 1</u></b> (prompt on \"Explorer\")", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Astronomy"}, {"question": "In 2017, the ARSA military organization launched attacks in this country's Arakan, or Rakhine, State. This country's government conducted Operation Dragon King under the orders of the socialist dictator Ne Win. In February 2021, a leader of this country, who had earlier won the Nobel Peace Prize, was overthrown in a Tatmadaw coup. For ten points, name this Southeast Asian country formerly led by Aung San Suu Kyi [[CHEE]] where over 500,000 Muslim Royhinga refugees have fled to neighboring Bangladesh since 2017.", "answer": "<b><u>Myanmar</u></b> (or Republic of the Union of <b><u>Myanmar</u></b>; or Pyidaunzu Thanm\u0103da <b><u>My\u0103ma</u></b> Nainngandaw; accept <b><u>Burma</u></b>)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "In reference to this figure, scientist Olesya Turkina said, \"We did not learn enough from the mission to justify the death of [this astronaut].\" A monument depicts this figure cradled by hands whose digits double as rockets, a part of the larger \"Monument to the Conquerors of Space.\" Scientist Vladimir Yazdovsky trained this cosmonaut to eat a specialized gel and kept her in progressively smaller cages to prep her for spaceflight. The term \"Muttnik\" was given to, for ten points, what Moscow stray dog, the first animal to orbit earth?", "answer": "<b><u>Laika</u></b> [[LYE-kah]] (accept \"<b><u>Muttnik</u></b>\" before mentioned)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "An ancient inscription banning this event was discovered in Tiriolo, Italy in 1640. Investigations of these events were conducted by Spurius Postumius Albinus [[ahl-BEE-nooss]] and Quintus Marcius Philippus. Hispala Faecenia [[fay-keh-NEE-ah]] was awarded 100,000 bronze coins for giving her testimony about these events. The Legislation of 186 states that these events were to be overlooked by the Senate. Traditions of these events were accounted for by Livy in his <em>History of Rome</em>. For ten points, what unofficial festivals celebrated the Greco-Roman god of wine?", "answer": "<b><u>Bacchanal</u></b>ia (accept <b><u>Bachanal</u></b>s; prompt on \"festivals of Bacchus\" and similar answers)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "A strike against this body due to its exclusion of Polish members may have been the first-known strike in American history. A malaria outbreak affected the first session of this body, at which 22 members were present. A speech given in front of this body included one man exclaiming, \u201cIf this be treason, make the most of it!\u201d A restored Capitol in Williamsburg is sometimes used by legislators to honor this body that was part of its state\u2019s General Assembly. Established in 1642, for ten points, what was this early legislative body of Virginia?", "answer": "Virginia House of <b><u>Burgesses</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Bayezid II claimed that this edict was foolish since it \u201c[gave him the] national treasure\u201d of one country. This edict gave rise to a \u201ccrypto\u201d group that continued the practice it sought to ban by July 31st of the year it was ordered. A campaign conducted a century prior by Ferrand Martinez aimed to accomplish the same result as this edict, which sought to curb its non-<em>converso</em> population. Preceded by a number of pogroms against the Sephardi, for ten points, what was this edict which expelled the Jews from Spain?", "answer": "<b><u>Alhambra Decree</u></b> (accept Edict of <b><u>Granada</u></b>; accept <b><u>Decreto de la Alhambra</u></b>; accept word forms for Edict of <b><u>Explusion</u></b> of <b><u>Jew</u></b>s from <b><u>Spain</u></b>; prompt on partial answers)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "The idea for this speech came from another given by Franklin Roosevelt about \u201cFala.\u201d This speech\u2019s orator flew to Los Angeles to give this address on television, and in this speech, he encouraged listeners to voice their support for him by calling the Republican National Committee. This speech was named after a cocker spaniel given as a gift to its speaker\u2019s children. For ten points, identify this speech given by California senator Richard Nixon regarding accusations of improper financial reimbursement.", "answer": "<b><u>Checkers</u></b> Speech", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "In the 1980s, a suit was launched by McGraw-Hill against the estate of this author over royalty payments for an unfinished memoir regarding his conversations with Medgar Evers and other Civil Rights figures. This author of <em>Remember This House</em> challenged the Nation of Islam as being equally as wrongheaded as white supremacy in his essay \"Down at the Cross.\" Many of this man's essays, including \"The Harlem Ghetto\" and \"White Man's Guilt,\" were included in his collection <em>The Price of the Ticket</em>. For ten points, name this Black novelist and author of <em>The Fire Next Time</em>.", "answer": "James <b><u>Baldwin</u></b> (or James Arthur <b><u>Baldwin</u></b>)", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Misc Literature"}, {}, {"question": "This object was described as \u201chairy and fierce\u201d by Bartolomeo of Platina. During a campaign in Belgrade, this object supposedly led \"[mathematicians to declare] that there would follow grievous pestilence.\" This object was referred to as an \u201cInstrument of the Devil\u201d by Pope Callixtus III, who excommunicated it. The <em>Anglo-Saxon Chronicle</em> describes this object as a \u201cportent...from the heavens\u201d that appeared prior to the Battle of Hastings. Compared by Giotto to the star of Bethlehem, for ten points, what is this regularly appearing comet?", "answer": "<b><u>Halley\u2019s</u></b> Comet (accept Comet <b><u>Halley</u></b>; accept 1P/<b><u>Halley</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This ambassador made a formal petition to Boutros Boutros-Ghali to not run for a second term as UN Secretary-General, instead offering him a foundation to run, which he declined. In a controversial <em>60 Minutes</em> interview, this politician said that half a million Iraqi children dying due to sanctions was \"worth it,\" though that number was later determined to have been fabricated. For ten points, name this first female Secretary of State who served under the second Clinton administration and died in March 2022.", "answer": "Madeleine <b><u>Albright</u></b> (or Madeleine Jana <b><u>Korbel</u></b>; or Marie Jana <b><u>Korbel</u></b>ov\u00e1)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "The creation of this state was preceded by the assassination of a military leader called the \u201cOld Marshal.\u201d The erroneous belief that the pope established diplomatic relations with this state is partly attributed to a film directed by Bernardo Bertolucci. That film, <em>The Last Emperor</em>, is about a leader of this state who ruled during the <em>Kangde</em> era. Harbin was the largest city in this state, where the Han formed a majority despite this state being named for a different ethnic group. For ten points, name this Japanese puppet state in China.", "answer": "<b><u>Manchukuo</u></b> (accept <b><u>State of Manchuria</u></b>; accept <b><u>Empire of Manchuria</u></b>; accept Empire of <b><u>Great Manchuria</u></b>; prompt on \u201cManchuria\u201d)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "John Gregory Tierney was the first casualty during this project, in which rocks were cleared by a group of \u201chigh scalers.\u201d A political cartoon reading \u201cIt Can\u2019t Be Done, Mr. Ickes [[IK-ees]]!\u201d references the naming dispute over this project, which Six Companies, Inc. won a bidding war to carry out. Found in the Black Canyon, this structure spans both Mohave and Clark Counties and impounded the Lake Mead reservoir. Located near Las Vegas, for ten points, what is this Depression-era project named for a Republican president?", "answer": "<b><u>Hoover Dam</u></b> (accept <b><u>Boulder Dam</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>This occupation, which began under the Medicis in the 16th century, includes</u></b> <b><u>Janet Collins, who refused to work for a company in Monte Carlo since she would have</u></b> <b><u>had to paint her face and skin white. A group of five Native American women in this</u></b> <b><u>profession, including Myra Yvonne (+)</u> Chouteau and Rosella Hightower, were named the Five Moons. The short-term wife of George Balanchine, (*) </b>Maria Tallchief, held this profession. For ten points, name this profession of Misty Copeland, who became the first African-American principal of ABT after performing in works like Tchaikovsky's <em>The</em> <em>Sleeping Beauty</em>.", "answer": "<b><u>Ballerina</u></b> (accept Prima <b><u>Ballerina</u></b>; accept <b><u>Ballet</u></b> dancer; prompt on \"dancer\" or \"choreographer\")", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Dance"}, {"question": "<b><u>A leader of this group formed the town of Jerusalem near Penn Yan and</u></b> <b><u>attracted young followers known as \"Universal.\" That leader of this group shunned</u></b> <b><u>their birth name and gendered pronouns and was known as Public Universal Friend.</u></b> <b><u>(+)</u> A founder of a colony of this group signed a peace treaty at Shackamaxon with the Lenape [[leh-NAH-pee]] chief, Tamanend. That man, who was given land by Charles II as debt repayment, befriended a founder of this religious group, George (*) </b>Fox. For ten points, name this Christian sect followed by William Penn.", "answer": "<b><u>Quaker</u></b>s (accept Religious Society of <b><u>Friends</u></b> before \"friends\" is mentioned)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Despite outnumbering an opposing force by roughly five to one, this</u></b> <b><u>organization lost over one-fourth of its members who participated in the Siege of</u></b> <b><u>Clonmel. George Monck led one part of this group with whom the Agitators and the</u></b> <b><u>Levellers argued (+)</u> over the form of its country\u2019s constitution during the Putney Debates. Eschewing tents, this group often quartered in nearby buildings and employed dragoons in battles at Dunbar and Preston. Supporting the (*) </b>Protectorate, for ten points, what was this army created by the reform-minded Oliver Cromwell?", "answer": "<b><u>New Model</u></b> Army (prompt on descriptive or partial answers)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>During an 1877 pogrom against people of this ethnicity in California, Mayor</u></b> <b><u>Andrew Jackson Bryant created a Committee of Safety to counter attacks on</u></b> <b><u>businesses like Mission Woolen Mills. After rumors that people of this ethnicity \"were</u></b> <b><u>killing whites wholesale,\" a (+)</u> mob killed 500 people of this ethnicity in Los Angeles in what some historians consider the largest mass lynching in American history. At least 28 miners of this ethnicity were killed in the Wyoming town of Rock (*) </b>Springs. For ten points, name this ethnicity, members of which were the subject of a namesake \"Exclusion Act.\"", "answer": "<b><u>Chinese</u></b>-Americans (accept <b><u>Han</u></b> Chinese; accept People from <b><u>China</u></b> and similar answers; prompt on \"Asian\" or \"East Asian\")", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Jozef Groll became a key innovator in this industry by using a \"noble\"</u></b> <b><u>ingredient produced near the city of \u017datec [[ZHAH-tek]], or Saaz. A trademark dispute</u></b> <b><u>in this industry featured uses of the name of the city of \u010cesk\u00e9-Bud\u011bjovice [[CHES-keh</u></b> <b><u>boo-DEH-yoh-vit-seh]]. Carl (+)</u> von Linde's development of refrigeration essentially eliminated this industry's use of caves for storage. One of the most important laws regulating this industry was the Reinheitsgebot [[rine-HITES-geh-boht]], which was adopted in (*) </b>Bavaria in 1516. For ten points, name this industry whose 19th century German-American titans included Eberhard Anheuser and Adolphus Busch.", "answer": "<b><u>Beer</u></b> industry (accept <b><u>Brewing</u></b> industry or equivalents; prompt on \"Alcohol\")", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>An opera by this composer includes characters such as Rambo, Molqi, and</u></b> <b><u>Marilyn and explores the history of Israeli-Palestinian relations, telling the story of a</u></b> <b><u>Jewish passenger on the hijacked</u> </b><em><b><u>Achille Lauro</u></b></em><b><u>. In another opera by this man, quotes</u></b> <b><u>from the</u> </b><em><b><u>Bhagavad Gita</u></b></em><b><u> (+)</u> are interwoven with declassified U.S. government documents about the atomic bomb. Chairman Mao dances the foxtrot in the last act of an opera by this composer about a (*) </b>president's visit abroad. For ten points, name this composer of the operas <em>The Death of Klinghoffer</em>, <em>Doctor Atomic</em>, and <em>Nixon in China</em>.", "answer": "John Coolidge <b><u>Adams</u></b> (do not accept \"John Luther Adams\")", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Opera"}, {"question": "<b><u>Thomas Edison declared that he was afraid of this man\u2019s discovery after one of</u></b> <b><u>his assistants had to get both of their arms amputated and died shortly after. An</u></b> <b><u>apparatus consisting of a Crookes tube and a screen painted with barium</u></b> <b><u>platinocyanide (+)</u> led to this scientist\u2019s most notable discovery. This scientist\u2019s wife reportedly exclaimed, \u201cI have seen my death!\u201d after examining a photograph (*) </b>of her hand. Lending his name to a type of radiation, for ten points, what German physicist discovered the X-ray?", "answer": "Wilhelm <b><u>R\u00f6ntgen</u></b> (or Wilhelm Conrad <b><u>R\u00f6ntgen</u></b>; accept <b><u>R\u00f6ntgen</u></b> radiation)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This movement forced Sultan Abdul Hamid II to revive the parliamentary</u></b> <b><u>period in 1908, shortly after this entity organized the Committee of Union and</u></b> <b><u>Progress. Operation Nemesis was a retaliatory mission to assassinate the Three</u></b> <b><u>Pashas (+)</u> of this organization, successfully targeting both Mehmed Talaat Pasha and Cemal [[keh-MAHL]] Pasha. The Assyrian and (*) </b>Armenian genocides during the First World War were executed by, for ten points, what revolutionary group in charge of the Ottoman Empire immediately prior to its dissolution?", "answer": "<b><u>Young Turk</u></b>s (accept <b><u>J\u00f6n T\u00fcrk</u></b>ler; accept <b><u>Committee of Union and Progress</u> </b>before mentioned; prompt on \"Turks\")", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Much of what is today this state was ceded after General Lewis Cass presided</u></b> <b><u>over the negotiations of the Treaty with the Chippewa. A Potawatomi [[pah-tah-WAH-</u><u>toh-mee]] militia massacred frontiersmen in this modern state in the Battle of St.</u></b> <b><u>Joseph (+)</u> during the larger Pontiac's War. In exchange for halting the Toledo War with neighboring Ohio, this state was given the (*) </b>Upper Peninsula by the Jackson administration. Antoine Cadillac founded, for ten points, what Midwest state's city of Detroit?", "answer": "<b><u>Michigan</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}